but wait there's more we also have data
dependencies that can cause pipeline
stalls consider these two instructions
we add R2 and R3 put the result in R1
then the subtract instruction here takes
R1 and uses it to compute R seven we say
that the subtract instruction has a data
dependence on this ad in fact we can
have this data dependence and there
could be another instruction that
produces
R8 that the subtract also depends on
when we have a data dependence that
means that we cannot just do these
instructions like they were loads of
laundry that have nothing to do with
each other we have to have the ad
produce R1 before the subtract can use
it this type of data dependence is
called a read after write dependence we
read something after it has been written
and that order needs to be preserved
this type of dependence is also called
flow dependence because the data flows
from one instruction to the other and it
is also called true dependence because
there is really a dependence as in the
subtract needs the add to finish before
it because the value doesn't exist until
the ad is finished so again this type of
dependen is called raw or read after
write or flow or true dependence there
are two other types of data dependencies
let's say say that there is later a
multiply instruction that takes R5 and
R6 and produces R1 so that later
instructions will use that R1 as the
result of the multiplication so for this
dependence we say that's a raw lower
through dependence there is a dependence
between the ADD and the multiply the add
needs to finish first and then the
multiply needs to finish because we want
the result of the multiply to end up as
the final value of R1 if if we let the
ad finish later then R1 produced by the
ad will be left in the R1 so subsequent
instructions would see that value which
would be wrong this type of dependence
is called a right after right or an
output dependence basically the final
result or the output for R1 is what's
affected and right after right simply
because they're both writing and we need
to preserve the order of the rights this
right should happen after this right the
third type of dependence
is here the subtract needs to finish
reading
R1 before multiply can be allowed to
over write it this type of dependence is
called Write after read because the
write needs to happen after this read
and it is also called anti-dependence
because it sort of reverses the order of
the flow dependencies for reasons we
will see later these two types of
dependencies are called false or name
dependencies so we have true
dependencies which are these raw
dependencies or flow dependencies and we
have false or name
dependencies that have to do with
overwriting a value that somebody has
written or read previously or at least
should read or write previously now we
have a read after write write after
write and write after readed dependence
so how about a read after red dependence
that's the only one that is Miss missing
here let's say we have two ads both of
which are reading R three read after
read is not a
dependence because these two
instructions don't need to be done in
the order of that dependence pretty much
we can reorder these two instructions
they will still read the correct value
of R3 so that is why this is not a
dependence the second instruction
doesn't depend on the first one it can
be done before or after it